you
Krishnamurti in dialogue with Dr. Alan
W. Anderson. J. Krishnamurti was born in
South India and educated in England. For
the past 40 years he has been speaking
in the United States, Europe, India,
Australia, and other parts of the world.
From the outset of his life's
work he repudiated all connections with
organized religions and ideologies and said that
his only concern was to set men
absolutely unconditionally free. He is the
author of many books, among them the
Awakening of Intelligence, The Urgency of
Change, Freedom from the Known, and The
Flight of the Eagle. This is one
of a series of dialogues between Krishnamurti
and Dr. Alan W. Anderson, who
is professor of religious studies at San
Diego State University where he teaches
Indian and Chinese scriptures and the
oracular tradition. Dr. Anderson, a
published poet, received his degree from
Columbia University and the Union
Theological Seminary. He has been honored
with a Distinguished Teaching Award
from the California State Universities.
Mr. Krishnamurti, during our conversations
one thing has emerged for
me with, I'd say, an arresting force and
that is, on the one hand we've been
talking about thought and knowledge in
terms of a dysfunctional relationship to
it, but never once have you said
that we should get rid of thought. You've
never said that knowledge as such
in itself has something profoundly the
matter with it. Therefore
the relationship between intelligence and
thought arises, and the question of what
seems to be that which maintains a
creative relationship between intelligence
and thought, perhaps some
primordial activity which abides, and in
thinking on this I wondered whether you
would agree that perhaps in the history
of human existence the concept of God
has been generated out of a
relationship to this abiding activity, which concept
has been very badly abused, and it
raises the whole question of the phenomenon of
religion itself. I wondered if we might discuss that today.
Yes. You know, the word like religion, love
or God, has almost lost all its meaning.
They have abused these words so
enormously. A religion has become a vast
superstition, a great propaganda,
incredible beliefs and superstitions,
worship of images made by the hand or
by the mind. So when we talk about
religion, I would like, if I may, to be
quite clear that we are, both of us, are
using the word religion in the real sense
of that word, not in the either Christian
or the Hindu or the Muslim or the Buddhist
or all the stupid things that are going on
in this country in the name of religion.
I think the word religion means gathering together
all energy at all levels – physical, moral,
spiritual – at all levels, gathering all this energy
which will bring about a great attention.
And in that attention there is no frontier,
and then from there move to meet – that is
the meaning of that word – the gathering of total energy
to understand what thought cannot possibly
capture. Thought is never new, never free,
and therefore it is always conditioned and
fragmentary and so on, which we discussed.
So religion is not a thing put together by
thought or by fear or by the pursuit of satisfaction
and pleasure, but something totally beyond
all this, which isn't romanticism, speculative
belief or sentimentality. And I think if we
could keep to the meaning of that word, putting
all aside all the superstitious nonsense that is
going on in the world in the name
of religion, which has become really quite
a circus, however beautiful it is, then I
think we could from there start, if you will,
if you agree to the meaning of that word.
I've been thinking as you've been speaking
that in the biblical tradition there are actual
statements from the prophets which seem to
point to what you're saying. Such things
come to mind as Isaiah's taking the part
of the divine when he says, My thoughts are
not your thoughts, my ways not your ways,
as high as the heavens are above the earth
so are my thoughts and your thoughts, so
stop thinking about me in that sense, and don't
try to find a means to me that you've
contrived, since my ways are higher than your ways. And
then I was thinking while you were
speaking concerning this act of attention, this gathering
together of all energies of the whole man,
the very simple, be still and know that I'm
God, be still. It's amazing when one thinks
of the history of religion how little attention
has been paid to that as compared with ritual.
And I think when we lost touch with
nature, with the universe, with the clouds, lakes,
birds, when we lost touch with all that,
then the priest came in, then all the superstition,
fears, exploitation, all that began. The priest
became the mediator between the human and
the so-called divine. And I believe, if you have read...
ركويتاً
or I was told about it
because I don't read all this,
that there, in the first way round,
there is no mention of God at all.
There is only this worship of something immense,
expressed in nature, in the earth,
in the clouds, in the trees,
in the beauty of vision.
But that being very, very simple,
the priest said, that's too simple.
A. Let's mix it up. K. Let's mix it up,
let's confuse it a little bit. And then began.
I believe this is traceable
from the ancient Vedas to present time,
where the priest became the interpreter,
the mediator, the explainer, the exploiter,
the man who said, this is right, this is wrong,
you must believe this, or you
go to perdition, and so on.
He generated fear.
Not the adoration of beauty,
not the adoration of life
lived totally, wholly without conflict,
but something placed outside there,
beyond and above what he considered to be God,
and made propaganda for that.
So, I feel if we could, from the beginning,
use the word religion in the simplest way,
that is, the gathering of all energy
so that there is total attention,
and in that quality of attention
the immeasurable comes into being.
Because, as we said the other day,
the measurable is the mechanical,
which the West has cultivated,
made marvellous, technologically, physically,
medicine, science, biology, and so on,
which has made the world so superficial,
mechanical, worldly, materialistic,
and that is spreading all over the world.
And in reaction to that,
this materialistic attitude,
there are all these superstitious, nonsensical,
unreasoned religion that is going on.
I don't know if you saw the other day
the absurdity of these gurus coming from India
and teaching the West how to meditate,
how to hold breath, how they say,
I am God, worship me, and falling there.
It has become so absurd,
and childish, so utterly immature.
All that indicates the degradation of the word religion,
and the human mind that can accept
this kind of circus and idiocy.
Now, please, sir.
A.S. – I was thinking
of a remark of Sri Aurobindo's
in a study that he made of the Veda,
where he traced its decline in the sentence.
He said it issues as language from sages,
then it falls to the priests,
and then after the priests it falls to the scholars
or the academicians.
But in that study there
was no statement that I found
as to how it ever fell to the priests.
And I was wondering whether...
K.P. – Isn't this fairly simple, sir?
A.S. – Yes, please.
K.P. – Isn't this fairly simple,
how the priests got hold of the whole business?
Because a man
is so concerned with his own petty little affairs,
petty little desires and ambitions, superficiality,
he wants something a little more.
He wants a little more romantic, a little more sentimental,
something other than the daily, beastly routine of living.
So he looks somewhere and the priest says,
hey, come over here, I've got the goods.
I think it's very simple
how the priests have come in.
You see it in India,
you see it in the West,
you see it everywhere where man begins to...
be concerned with daily living,
the daily operation of bread and butter and house
and all the rest of it.
He demands something more than that.
He says, after all, I'll die,
but there must be something more.
A.S. – So fundamentally it's
a matter of securing for himself
some heavenly grace...
A.S. – ...some heavenly grace that will preserve him
against falling into this mournful round
of coming to be and passing away.
Thinking of the past on the one hand,
anticipating the future on the other,
you're saying he falls out of the present now.
K. Yes, that's right. A.S. – I understand.
K. So if we could keep
to that meaning of that word, religion,
then from there the question arises,
can the mind be so attentive in the total sense
that the unnameable comes into being?
You see, personally,
I've never read any of these things,
Vedas, Bhagavad Gita, Upanishads, all the rest of it,
or any philosophy,
but I questioned everything.
A.S. – Yes.
K. Not questioned only, but observed.
And one sees the absolute necessity
of a mind that's completely quiet.
Because it's only out of quietness
you perceive what is happening.
If I am chattering, I won't listen to you.
If my mind is constantly rattling away,
what you are saying, I won't pay attention.
To pay attention means to be quiet.
A.S. – There have been some priests, apparently,
who usually ended up in a
great deal of trouble for it,
there have been some priests who had,
it seems, a grasp of this.
I was thinking of Meister Eckhart's remark that
whoever is able to read the book of nature
doesn't need any scriptures at all.
K. At all. That's just it.
A.S. Of course, he ended up in great trouble.
Yes, he had a bad time
toward the end of his life,
and after he died the church denounced him.
Of course, of course.
Organised belief as church and all the rest of it
is too obvious.
It isn't subtle, it hasn't
got the quality of real depth
and real spirituality. You know what it is.
A.S. Yes, I do.
K. So, I'm asking,
what is the quality of a mind,
and therefore heart and brain,
what is the quality of a mind
that can perceive something
beyond the measurement of thought?
What is the quality of a mind?
Because that quality is the religious mind.
That quality of a mind that is capable,
that has this feeling of being sacred in itself,
and therefore is capable of seeing something
immeasurably sacred.
A.S. The word devotion seems to imply this
when it's grasped in its proper sense.
To use your earlier phrase,
gathering together toward a one-pointed attentive.
K. Would you say attention is one-pointed?
A.S. No, I didn't mean to
imply focus when I said one-pointed.
I meant rather integrated into itself
as utterly quiet and unconcerned
about taking thought for what
is ahead or what is behind.
Simply being there.
The word there isn't good either,
because it suggests that there's a where,
and a here, and all the rest of it.
It is very difficult to
find, it seems to me, language,
to do justice to what you're saying,
precisely because when we speak,
utterance is in time, and it is progressive.
It has a quality, doesn't it?
More like music than we see in graphic art.
You can stand before a picture,
whereas to hear music and grasp its theme,
you virtually have to wait
until you get to the end
and gather it all up.
And with language you have the same difficulty.
K. No, I think, sir, wouldn't you,
when we are enquiring into this problem,
what is the nature and the structure of a mind,
and therefore the quality of a mind
that is not only sacred and holy in itself,
but is capable of seeing something immense.
As we were talking the other day about suffering,
the personal and the sorrow of the world,
it isn't that we must suffer.
Suffering is there.
Every human being has a dreadful time with it,
and there is suffering of the world.
And it isn't that one must go through it,
but as it is there, one
must understand it and go beyond it.
And that's one of the qualities of a religious mind,
in the sense we are using that word,
that is incapable of suffering.
It has gone beyond it,
which doesn't mean that it becomes callous.
On the contrary, it is a passionate mind.
A. One of the things
that I have thought much about
during our conversations is language itself.
On the one hand we say,
such a mind, as you have been describing,
is one that is present to suffering.
It does nothing to push
it away, on the one hand.
و
لكن
it is somehow able to contain it,
not put it in a vase or a barrel
and contain it in that sense.
And yet the very word itself, to suffer,
means to under-carry,
and it seems close to understand.
Over and over again in our conversations
I've been thinking about the customary way
in which we use language
as a use that deprives us
of really seeing the glory
of what the word points to itself in itself.
I was thinking about the word religion
when we were speaking earlier.
Scholars differ as to where that came from.
On the one hand some
say that it means to bind.
K. Biner, really a guarantee.
A. They spoke about that.
And then others say, no, no, it means the numinous,
or the splendour that cannot be exhausted by thought.
It seems to me that, wouldn't you say,
there is another sense to bind
that is not a negative one,
in the sense that if one
is making this act of attention,
one isn't bound as with cords of ropes,
but one is there, or here.
K. Now again, let's be clear.
When we use the word attention,
there is a difference between concentration and attention.
Concentration is exclusion.
I concentrate.
That is, bring all my thinking to a certain point.
And therefore it is excluding,
building a barrier
so that it can focus its whole attention on that,
whole concentration on that.
Whereas attention is something
entirely different from concentration.
In that there is no exclusion,
in that there is no resistance,
in that there is no effort,
and therefore no frontier, no limits.
A. How would you feel about
the word receptive in this respect?
K. Again, who is it that is to receive?
A. Already we have made a division with that word.
I think the word attention
is a really very good word,
because it not only understands concentration,
not only sees the duality of reception,
the receiver and the received,
and also it sees the nature of duality
and the conflict of the opposites.
And attention means
not only the brain giving its energy,
but also the mind, the heart, the nerve,
the total entity, the total human mind,
giving all its energy to perceive.
I think that is the meaning
of that word for me, at least.
To be attentive, attend.
Not concentrate, attend.
That means listen, see, give your heart to it,
give your mind to it,
give your whole being to it, to attend.
Otherwise you can't attend.
If I am thinking about something else, I can't attend.
If I am hearing my own voice, I can't attend.
A. There is a metaphorical use
of the word waiting in scripture.
It is interesting that in English too
we use the word attendant
in terms of one who waits on.
I am trying to penetrate the notion of waiting
and patience in relation to this.
K. Sir, waiting again means
one who is waiting for something.
Again there is a duality in that.
And when you wait, you are expecting.
Again a duality.
One who is waiting, about to receive.
So, if we could for the moment
hold ourselves to that word, attention,
then we should enquire
what is the quality of
a mind that is so attentive
that it has understood, lives, acts
in relationship and responsibility as behaviour,
and has no fear psychologically in that we talked about,
and therefore understands the movement of pleasure,
then we come to the
point, what is such a mind?
I think it would be worthwhile if we could discuss
the nature of hurt.
A. Of hurt. Yes.
Why human beings are hurt.
All people are hurt.
A. Both the physical and the psychological.
K. Psychological, especially.
A. Especially the psychological.
K. Physically we can tolerate it,
we can bear up with the pain and say,
well, I won't let it interfere with my thinking,
I won't let it corrode my psychological quality of mind.
I can watch over it,
the mind can watch over that.
But the psychological hurts are much more important
and difficult to grapple with and understand.
I think it is necessary because
a mind that is hurt is not an innocent mind.
The very word in innocent comes from Noir, chérez,
not to hurt, a mind
that is incapable of being hurt.
And there is a great beauty in that.
A. Yes, there is.
It's a marvellous word.
We have usually used it
to indicate a lack of something.
Yes, and there it was turned upside down again.
A. Yes, and there it was turned upside down again.
K. And the Christians have made
it such an absurd thing of it.
A. Yes, I understand that.
K. So, I think we ought to, when discussing religion,
we ought to enquire very,
very deeply the nature of hurt.
Because if a mind that is
not hurt is an innocent mind,
and you need this quality of innocency,
to be so totally attentive.
A. If I have been
following you correctly, I think maybe
you would say, wouldn't you, that one becomes hurt
when he starts thinking about thinking that he is hurt.
K. Look, sir, it's much deeper than that, isn't it?
From childhood,
the parents compare the child with another child.
A. But that's when that thought arises.
K. There it is. When you compare, you are hurting.
A. Yes.
K. No, we say, but we do it.
A. Oh, yes, of course we do it.
K. Therefore, is it possible
to educate a child without comparison,
without imitation,
and therefore never get hurt in that way?
And one is hurt because one
has built an image about oneself.
The image which has built about
oneself is a form of resistance,
a wall between you and me.
And when you touch that wall
at its tender point, I get hurt.
So, not to compare in education,
not to have an image about oneself.
That's one of the most important things in life,
If you have, you are inevitably going to be hurt.
Suppose one has an image that one is very good,
or that one should be a great success,
or that one has great capacities, gifts,
and the images that one builds.
Inevitably, you are going to come and prick it.
Inevitably, accidents and incidents happen,
that's going to break that, and one gets hurt.
A. Doesn't this raise the question
of name, the use of name?
K. Name, form.
The child is given a name,
the child identifies himself with a name.
K. Yes, the child can identify itself,
but without the image, just a name.
Brown, Mr Brown. There is nothing to it.
But the moment he builds an image,
that Mr Brown is socially,
morally different, superior, or inferior,
ancient, or comes from a very old family,
belongs to a certain higher class, aristocracy,
the moment that begins,
and when that is encouraged and sustained by thought,
snobbism, you know, the whole of it,
then you are inevitably going to be hurt.
A. Then what you are saying, I take it,
is that the radical confusion here
is involved in imagining oneself to be his name.
K. Yes, identification with the name, with the body,
with the idea of socially different,
that your parents, your grandparents
were lords, or this or that,
you know, the whole snobbism of England and all that,
and different kind of snobbism in this country.
A. We speak in the language of preserving a name.
K. And in India it is the Brahmin, the non-Brahmin,
the whole business of that.
So, through education,
through tradition, through propaganda,
we have built an image about ourselves.
A. Is there a relation here in terms of religion,
would you say, to the refusal, for instance,
in the Hebraic tradition, to pronounce the name of God?
K. The name.
The word is not the thing, anyhow.
So you can pronounce it, not pronounce it.
No, if you know the word is never the thing.
The description is never the
described, then it doesn't matter.
A. One of the reasons
I've always been, over the years,
deeply drawn to the study of the roots of words
is simply because, for the most part,
they point to something very concrete.
It's either a thing, or it's a gesture,
more often than not, it's some act.
K. Quite, quite. A. Some act.
When I used the phrase, thinking about thinking before,
I should have been more careful of my words
and referred to mulling over the image,
which would have been a much
better way to put it, wouldn't it?
Yes.
K. So, can a child be educated
never to get hurt?
And I have heard professors, scholars say,
a child must be hurt in
order to live in the world.
And when I asked him,
do you want your child to be hurt,
he kept absolutely quiet.
He was just talking theoretically.
Now, unfortunately, through education,
through social structure
and the nature of our society in which we live,
we have been hurt, we have images about ourselves
which are going to be hurt,
and is it possible not to create images at all?
I don't know if I'm making myself clear.
A. You are.
Suppose I have an image about myself,
which I have, unfortunately.
If I have an image,
is it possible to wipe it away,
to understand it and therefore dissolve it,
and never to create a new image about myself?
You understand?
Living in a society, being educated,
I have built an image, inevitably.
Now, can that image be wiped away?
A. Wouldn't it disappear with
this complete act of attention?
K. That's what I'm coming to, gradually.
It would totally disappear.
But I must understand how this image is born.
I can't just say, well, I'll wipe it out.
よっ
use attention as a means of wiping it out.
It doesn't work that way.
In understanding the image, in understanding the hurt,
in understanding the education
in which one has been brought up,
the family, the society, all that,
in understanding of that,
out of that understanding comes the attention,
not attention first and then wipe it out.
You can't attend if I am hurt.
You understand? If I am hurt, how can I attend?
Because that hurt is going to keep me,
consciously or unconsciously,
from this total attention.
A.S. The amazing thing, if I am understanding you correctly,
is that even in the study of the dysfunctional history,
provided I bring total attention to that,
there's going to be a non-temporal relationship
between the active attention and
the healing that takes place.
While I am attending, the thing is leaving.
We've got, inging along here, throughout.
Yes, exactly.
So, there are two questions involved.
Can the hurts be healed so
that not a mark is left?
Can future hurts be prevented completely,
not without any resistance? You follow?
Those are two problems.
And they can be understood only and resolved
when I give attention to the understanding of my hurts,
when I look at it, not translate it,
not wish to wipe them
away, just to look at it,
as we went into that question of perception,
just to see my hurts.
The hurts I have received, the insults, the negligence,
the casual word, the gesture, all those hurts.
And the language you only use, especially in this country.
You understand? A.S. Oh, yes.
There seems to be a
relationship between what you are saying
and one of the meanings of the word salvation.
To be...
K. Salvare, to save. A. To save.
To make whole. K. To make whole.
How can you be whole, sir, if you are hurt?
A. Impossible.
K. Therefore it is tremendously important
to understand this question. A. Yes, it is.
But I am thinking of
a child who comes to school,
who has already got a freight car filled with hurts.
We are not dealing with the
little one in the crib now.
We are already... K. Already hurt.
A. Already hurt. And hurt because it is hurt.
And it multiplies endlessly, doesn't it?
K. From that hurt he is violent. A. Yes.
K. From that hurt he
is frightened and therefore withdrawing.
From that hurt he will do neurotic things.
From that hurt he will
accept anything that gives him safety.
God, his idea of God is
a God who will never hurt.
A. Sometimes a distinction is
made between ourselves and animals
with respect to this problem.
An animal, for instance, that has been badly hurt,
will be disposed toward everyone
in terms of emergency and tack.
But over a period of time,
it might take three, four years
if the animal is loved.
So, sir, you said love. We haven't got that.
The parents haven't got love for their children.
They may talk about love.
Because the moment they compare the younger to the older,
they have hurt the child.
Your father was so clever,
you are such a stupid boy,
there you have begun.
In schools, when they give you marks,
it is a hurt, not
marks, it is a deliberate hurt.
And that is taught.
And from that there is violence,
there is every kind of aggression,
you know, all that takes place.
So how can a mind...
A mind cannot be made whole, or is whole,
unless this is understood very, very deeply.
A. The question that I had in mind before
regarding what we have been saying
is that this animal, if loved, will,
provided we are not dealing with brain damage or something,
will, in time, love in return.
But the thought is that with the human person,
love cannot be, in that sense, coerced.
It isn't that one would coerce the animal to love,
but that the animal, because innocent,
does, in time, simply respond, accept.
But then a human person is doing something
we don't think the animal is.
K. No, the human being is being hurt
and is hurting all the time.
A. Exactly.
While he is mulling over his hurt,
then he is likely to misinterpret
the very act of generosity and
love that is made toward him.
So we are involved in something very frightful here.
By the time the child comes
into school, he is seven years old.
K. He is already gone, finished, tortured.
There is the tragedy of
it, sir, that's what I mean.
A. Yes, I know.
And when you ask the question, as you have,
is there a way to educate
the child so that the child...
K. ...is never hurt?
That is part of education, that's part of culture.
Civilisation is hurting.
Sir, look, you see this everywhere, all over the world,
this constant comparison, constant imitation,
constant imitation, constant saying,
you are that, I must be like you.
I must be like Krishna, like Buddha, like Jesus.
You follow? That's a hurt.
Religions have hurt people.
A. The child is born to a hurt parent,
sent to a school where it
is taught by a hurt teacher.
Now you are asking, is there
a way to educate this child
so that the child recovers?
K. It is possible, sir. A. Yes, please.
K. That is, when the teacher realises,
when the educator realises he is
hurt and the child is hurt,
is aware of his hurt and
is aware also of the child's hurt,
then the relationship changes.
Then he will, in the very act of teaching,
whatever mathematics it is, whatever it is,
he is not only freeing himself from his hurt,
but also helping the child
to be free of his hurt.
After all, that is education.
To see that I, who
am the teacher, I am hurt.
I have gone through agonies of hurt,
and I want to help
that child not to be hurt.
And he has come to the school being hurt.
So I say, all right,
we both are hurt, my friends.
Let us see, let's help
each other to wipe it out.
That is the act of love.
A. Comparing the human organism with the animal,
I return to the question whether it is the case
that this relationship to another human being
must bring about this healing.
K. Obviously, sir, if relationship exists,
we said relationship can only exist
when there is no image between you and...
A. But let us say that there is a teacher
who has come to grips with
this in himself very, very deeply,
has, as you put it, gone into the question,
deeper, deeper and deeper,
has come to the place
where he no longer is hurt-bound.
K. Yes, sir.
A. The child that he meets,
or the young student that he meets,
or even the student his own age,
because we have adult education now.
Is a person who is hurt-bound, and will he not...
K. Transmitted that hurt to another?
A. No, no, will he not, because he is hurt-bound,
be prone to misinterpret the activity
of the one who is not hurt-bound?
K. But there is no person who is not hurt-bound,
except very, very few.
Look, sir, lots of things have happened to me, personally.
I have never been hurt.
I say this in all humility, in a real sense,
I don't know what it means to be hurt.
Things have happened to me,
people have done every kind of thing to me,
praised me, flattered me, kicked me around, everything.
It is possible.
And as a teacher, as
an educator, to see the child,
and it is my responsibility as educator
to see he is never hurt.
Not just teach some beastly subject.
This is far more important.
A. I think I have some
grasp of what you are talking about.
I don't think I could ever, in my wildest dreams,
say that I have never been hurt.
Though I do have difficulty, and have since a child,
I have even been taken to
task for it, dwelling on it.
I remember a colleague of mine
once saying to me with some time,
some testiness when we were discussing a situation
in which there was conflict in the faculty,
the trouble with you is you can't hate.
And it was looked upon as a disorder,
in terms of being unable to
make a focus towards the enemy
in such a way as
to devote total attention to that.
Sanity is taken for insanity.
A. So my reply to
him was simply, well, that's right,
and we might as well face it,
and I don't intend to do anything about that.
But it didn't help the
situation in terms of the interrelationship.
K. The question is then, in education,
can a teacher, educator, observe his hurts,
become aware of them,
and in his relationship with the student,
resolve his hurt and the student's hurt?
That's one problem.
It is possible if the teacher is really,
in the deep sense of the word, educator.
That is to cultivate.
And the next question, sir, from that arises,
is the mind capable of not being hurt,
knowing it has been hurt? You follow?
Not add more hurts.
These are two problems.
One, being hurt, that's the past,
and never to be hurt again.
Which doesn't mean I build a wall of resistance
that I withdraw, that I go off into a monastery,
or I become a drug addict,
or some silly things like that,
but no hurt. Is that possible?
You see the two questions?
Now, if...
That is, what is hurt?
What is the thing that is hurt?
You follow?
We said the physical hurt is
not the same as psychological hurt.
So we are dealing with psychological hurt.
What is the thing that is hurt?
The psyche?
The image which I have about myself?
A. It is an investment that I have in it.
K. Yes. It is my investment in myself.
A. Yes. I have divided myself off from myself.
K. Yes, in myself.
That means, why should I invest in myself?
What is myself?
You follow? A. Yes, I do.
K. In which I have to invest something.
What is myself?
All the words, the names, the qualities, the education,
the bank account, the furniture, the house, the herds,
all that is me.
A. In an attempt to
answer the question, what is myself,
I immediately must resort to all this stuff.
K. Obviously.
A. There is no other way.
And then I haven't got it.
Then I praise myself, because I must be so marvellous
as somehow to slip out.
I see what you mean.
I was thinking just a moment back,
when you were saying it is possible for the teacher
to come into relationship with the student,
so that a work of healing,
or an act of healing happens.
K. This is what I would
do if I was in a class.
That is the first thing I
would begin with, not some subject.
I say, look, you are hurt and I am hurt.
We are both of us hurt.
And to point out what hurt does,
how it kills people, how it destroys people,
out of that there is violence,
out of that there is brutality,
out of that I want to hurt people.
You follow? All that comes in.
I would spend ten minutes talking about that,
every day in different ways,
till both of us see it.
Then as an educator I will use the right word
and the student will use the right word.
There will be no gesture, there will be no...
We are both involved in it.
But we don't do that.
The moment we come into the class,
we pick up a book and then it goes off.
If I was an educator,
whether with the older people or with the younger people,
I would establish this relationship.
That is my duty, that is
my job, that is my function.
Not just to transmit some information.
A. Yes, that's really very profound.
I think one of the reasons that
what you have said is so difficult
for an educator reared within the whole academic...
K. Yes, because we are so vain.
A. Exactly.
We want not only to hear that it's possible
for this transformation to take place,
but we want it to be regarded as demonstrably proved,
and therefore not merely possible,
but predictably certain.
K. Certain, yes.
A. And then we are
back into the whole thing again.
K. Of course, then we are
back into the old rotten stuff.
Quite right.
A. Next time, could we take
up the relationship of love to this?
K. Yes.
A. I would very much enjoy that.
And it would seem to me...
K. We would all come together.
A. ...we would come together, in the gathering together.
K. Yes, I believe that.
This program...